Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817
    Recommending to Franklin's attention, his eldest son [Victor Mario Du Pont] who goes to America to complete his education by studying the conditions of a free country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Arthaud, Charles. Au Cap François
    Sending a work on questions of rural economy just published by Le Gercle des Philadesphes; desires one copy presented to the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Birkbeck and Blakes. London
    Sending receipt for a small box shipped in the "Convention," Capt. Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburgh
    Announcing their safe arrival after a journey of eighteen days; expense of living as dear as in Philadelphia. Amused by the sight of savings. Thinks the country will suit them better than this sad little town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 18; Biddle, Charles. Philadelphia
    Resignation of Mr. [John] Armstrong [Jr.] as Secretary to Council; desires to obtain the appointment; asks Franklin's friendship in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Pinckney, Thomas. Charleston, S.C
    No vessel at present ready to sail for New York; begs him to forward the enclosed commissions by the first safe opportunity; necessity of keeping their representation in Congress complete.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Mr. Swain will make Franklin a small payment, enough to show his (Childs's) good intentions; disadvantages under which he has worked; hopes Franklin's silence is not due to displeasure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 26; A.L.S. 1p.; La Luzerne, Chevalier de
    Appreciated Franklin's recommending Capt. John Earle to him; will serve him in every way in his power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 29; A.L. 4p.; Brillon, Mme
    Deaths of M. Brillon and her granddaughter, aged three; crushed by these two sorrows; news of her two daughters, their husbands and their combined household; begs him to write.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Jan., 1907, 435.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Gorham, Nathaniel. Boston
    Franklin's speech, made just before the close of the [Constitutional] Convention, calculated to prevent war and blood-shed; with his permission, desires a copy for publication; the great weight and influence it would have in New England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 October 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburgh
    Anxious concerning their letters and remittances from France; begs Franklin to forward them as soon as they arrive.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Sevier, John. State of Franklin
    Creek Indians still carrying on their depredations. Great results expected from the [Constitutional] Convention. Desiring Franklin's patronage and interest for their State; feeling among the Western Americans that their interests are neglected. Introducing Major Droomgoole, who goes to Congress with letters from the Cherokee Indians; his wish to act as Superintendent over some of the southern tribes; his influence among the Cherokee chiefs; recommends him warmly for the position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Guillotin, Joseph Ignace
    Thanking him for his gracious reception of Messrs. Saugrain [de Vigny] and Picque; sends the enclosed letters for them; impatient for the time to come to pay his respects to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 5; L.S. 2p.; Viguera Neveu, ----
    Forwarding a box of books arrived for Franklin from Madrid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Greene, Catharine. Boston
    Visiting Franklin's sister [Mecom]; expects to return home that day. News of friends. Account of her family, the marriages and occupations of her children. Mortified at the depravity of their State [Rhode Island].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbé de Marbois, François
    Reminding Franklin of certain astronomical observations by M. le [Comte] Granchain [de Sémerville] which were given a favorable reception some years before by the [American] Philosophical Society; M de Granchain presented to the Society as a candidate for membership, but by some error the Comte de Guichen was elected in his place; begs that this mistake may be corrected; also recommends for membership M. Moreau de St. Méry, who desires to present to the Society his work on the Laws and Constitution of Saint Domingo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 13; L.S. 1p.; Brienne, Chevalier de
    Forwarding a letter from M. Thomas, who begs that Franklin will act as a mediator in a business matter between him and Franklin's son-in-law [Richard Bache] and nephew [Jonathan Williams, Jr.]; asks him to consider this request favorably.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Thomas, Isaiah. Worcester
    Has reprinted an edition of Perry's Pronouncing English Dictionary, at his own risk and expense; desires to dedicate the first American edition to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Dulany, Walter. Bladensburg
    His wife suffering greatly from stone in the kidney; heard that Franklin obtained great relief from blackberry jelly; has tried it without result; if it was really successful in Franklin's case, begs for more particular information; requests an early answer as his wife is extremely ill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Smith, Sarah H. Baltimore
    Only daughter of Thomas Franklin; lately left a widow with five helpless children; miserly and unfeeling conduct of her brother James; her other brothers not in a position to help her; desires Franklin to do something for her children; their present destitute condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Croker, Henry Temple. St. Kitts
    Concerning Franklin's improved plan of a horizontal windmill; on trial, found it insufficient to overcome the resistance of canes, through it may grind corn or raise water; begs Franklin to lay the matter before the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Minister and Vestry of the German Lutheran Congregation. Philadelphia
    Requesting his presence at the speaking exercises to be performed in the German language at Zion Church.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 November 19; A.L.S. 6p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Sent the car and harness to Philadelphia. Rejoiced at the new Constitution of the United States; criticizes part of it; rails against ascendency of the Clergy. Trouble in the Netherlands; war averted. Death and funeral of the Duke of Rutland, Viceroy of Ireland. Eulogy of Lord Chatham. Desires the appointment of Consul for his son at Marseilles; recommends their having one in Dublin. Opposite his desk is Franklin's bust, on his left are the pictures of the American worthies and across from them is [Benedict] Arnold suspended by the heels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Carroll, Daniel. Annapolis
    Meeting of the House of Delegages; the presence of their deputies required to give information of the proceedings in [the Constitutional] Convention, attended with Messrs. [Daniel of St. Thomas] Jenifer, [James] McHenry, and [Luther] Martin; attack made on the Convention, on Washington and Franklin by anti-federalists; felt compelled to read them Franklin's speech on Representation given before the Convention, and also the one of September 17th; fears Franklin's displeasure on this head; has allowed no copies of the speeches to be taken; awaits his commands in the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Partridge, Elizabeth. Boston
    Sympathizes with his painful disorder; hopes he will be long spared to his country. Some of his letters to her destroyed by mice; begs him to rewrite the paragraph to which he referred.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 7; A.L.S. 1p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de
    Recommending to Franklin's kindness the Marquis de Chappe de Laisne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; L.S. [Justice] James Loughead. 1p.; Hellstede, Charles
    Complaining of the rough, rude and violent behavior in his house of two Constables who would have dragged his servant, John Bergman, away, had he not interfered; they said they belonged to Justice James Loughead's office and that they came for taxes; Bergman not taxable; begs Franklin to use his authority to prevent such extravagancies.
    Apology to the Consul annexed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Greene, Caty. Westerly [R. I.]
    Sending him a small bag of sweet corn. Longs to see him. News of her family; Mrs. General [Nathanael] Greene in good health and living at Hartford.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburgh
    Anxious about their letters from France; have bought a small boat and expect to leave Fort Pitt shortly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 12; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Quinn, Patrick
    Petitioning Franklin to obtain him employment in some of the public offices.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 12; L.S. 1p.; Rittenhouse, David. Philadelphia
    Certifying that he has been on board Mr. [John] Fitch's steam-boat when it was worked against both wind and tide; thinks it will meet with the encouragement it so justly deserves.
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Randolph, Gov. Edmund. Richmond
    Mr. Joseph Elam arrested in Philadelphia as a proper subject for the hospital [for the insane] there and of his subsequent escape; has done business with him for two years and found him intelligent and orderly; Mr. Elam afraid to return to Philadelphia on business without Franklin's protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 15; A.L. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Begging for news of the [Constitutional] Convention. Messrs. le Due d'Orleéans, l'Abbé Sabattier and Frelot, Counsellors of Parliament, still exiled; efforts made to obtain their retun. Promises of M. [Ferdinand] Grand to send the portrait by a sure hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Gorham, Nathaniel. Charlestown
    Happy effect attending the publication of Franklin's speech [in the Constitutional Convention]; read and applauded by almost every one; opinion of Franklin's old friends in Boston. Prospect very encouraging in South Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Hopkinson, Vires Acquirit Cedendo Francis. Philadelphia
    Meeting of the [American] Philosophical Society and the disposition of Mr. [John Hyacinth de] Magellan's annual premium; many dissatisfied with the manner in which the affair was conducted and entered on the minutes; desires Franklin to summon another meeting before the end of the month to reconsider the proceedings and revise the minutes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Weiss, L
    Application made to him as a magistrate by Mr. Henry Clawes to recover a debt from John Dean, Esq., member of the Supreme Executive Council; is uncertain whether such an act on his part would be counted a breach of privilege; has written the enclosed [1 p.] to Mr. Dean without result; desires Franklin's advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Armstrong, Col John. Carlisle
    [Richard] Wharton shall not lack recommendations for admittance to the Court of Carlisle. Dr. Nesbit and himself in favor of adopting the Constitution, keeping in view such Amendments as experience and a fittter time may point out; expects good results from the publication of Franklin's last speech in the Convention; pernicious effect of the minority's dissent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Randolph, Gov. Edmund. Richmond
    Pursuant to a Resolution of their General Assembly, encloses two copies of their Act concerning the Convention [to ratify the Constitution] to be held in June next; one copy intended for the Pennsylvania Legislature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbé de Marbois, François
    Writes on behalf of Jean Vicard, whose petition he encloses [2 p.]; account of his being forced to marry a woman of the town, who pretended that he was the father of her child; at present he is in prison for failing to support them; begs Franklin to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787 December 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Magaw, Rev Samuel
    Business of the [American] Philosophical Society; permitted their determination, respecting inventions that came nearest to the annual premium, to be inserted in one of the public papers; apologizes for seeming to act contrary to Franklin's opinion; explains his reasons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem 2p.; The Controller of Finances of Pennsylvania
    Statement for 1787.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787; L.S. 1p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Lately crossed the ocean with Com. [John] Paul Jones; takes advantage of his departure for Philadelphia to transmit to Dr. Franklin a letter from the Comtesse d'Houdetot and the 2d edition of the Farmers Letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1787 ?]; A.L. 4p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Recommending to America, the formation of a navy and the building of harbor defenses. Description of their Parliament; their late imperious Viceroy censured instead of impeached. Affairs in France; the National Assembly nearly completed their laws; attitude of King and Queen; La Fayette the Washington of Europe. War between the Brabanters and the Emperor Joseph. Mr. [Silas] Deane's vote in Ireland. [Conclusion missing.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 1p.; Rittenhouse, David. Philadelphia
    Account of experiments with cedar wood in coloring glass.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1787; A.L.S 2p.; Tobine, James K. Philadelphia
    Asks for help in obtaining employment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr.
    Requests Dr. Franklin to send the estimates of building, as bill for scantling amounts to more than the estimate. The bill for land will be published by [Eleazer] Oswald to-morrow, when it and the Alien's Bill will be called for.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Question of imperfections in the type.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Small, Alexander. London
    General òpinion in England that America had better adopt a limited form of government. English commercial prosperity. Mr. [Josiah] Wedgwood's beautiful earthenware. Advises a recall of American tories. Future of France. America likely to take Mexico from Spain.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 321; Bigelow, IX, 452).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, John. London
    Refers to his letter of April, 1786, accompanied by Dobson's Treatise on Fixed Air; relief obtained from the stone by drinking water impregnated with this air; sends a new apparatus which obviates the frequent burstings; would be glad to hear if it procures him ease. Iniquitous traffic of slaves; believes an end will be put to it soon. Hopes America will not create any orders of nobility or hereditary honors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Had promised himself the pleasure of communicating certain remarks on Franklin's observations on the gulf-stream [see "Maritime Observations," Lonodn, 1787]; prevented by his mother's serious illness; has sent her to Hackney for change of air; by Capt. Spruce they have sent Franklin a cheese.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Thomas, Isaiah. Worcester Mass
    Thanks him for the desired permission which, however, came too late for publication; delayed printing the dedication [of William Perry's Royal Standard English Dictionary] as long as possible, and finally inscribed it to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences; will make use of the liberty granted him in the next edition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Livingston, William. Elizebeth Town
    Announcing that the State Convention of New Jersey has unanimously ratified the Federal Constitution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Pagin, Pére. Paris
    Introducing M. Dupuy du Gurard a young man, whó has determined to seek employment in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 Janaury 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Sharp, Granville. Leadenhall St., London
    Acknowledging his election as member of the Pennsylvania Society for promoting the Abolition of Slavery; thinks a state which sanctions slave-dealing and salve-holding invites divine retribution; takes exception of two clauses in the new Federal Constitution (9th Section of 1st Article and 2d Section of 3d Article).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburgh
    Everything frozen including the river; obliged to postpone their departure until the spring. At present they are settled about three miles from Pittsburgh; their dissipation consists in felling trees and trapping game.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Davis, William. Boston
    His repeated losses, amounting to six thousand pounds; two promising sons killed in the war; can no longer provide for his family; when he was able, gave his services gratis to the public; begs Franklin to obtain some relief for his family without mentioning his name; would be grateful for some position which a man of his advanced years could fill; desires this letter burnt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Thomson, Charles
    Notice of the assembly of Congress and of the election of Cyrus Griffin as its President.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Limozin, Andrew. Havre-de-Grace
    Forwarding to Congress an Act passed in the King's Council for sundry favors granted to the American trade. Reminds him of the number of American prisoners who came from England to the above port in a destitute state, and of the assistance rendered them there; mentions his own part in relieving this distress; reminds Franklin of his promise to recommend him to Congress, if not for reimbursement—then for a reward; since then has performed the duties of Agent for the Untied States; desires to be legally appointed their Agent with power for his son to act as such in his absence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Lotbinière, Chartier de, marquis de
    The vigorous reply of the King of France to the deceitful and impudent message of the English Minsiter, has checked for a time England's fury against France for having aided the Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 30; L.S. 1p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Asking Franklin's opinion concerning Mr. [John] Fitch's steamboat; desires to know how far he thinks it could be rendered useful for inland navigation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis. Poughkeepsie
    Regrets that Franklin's grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache] has been disappointed. Appreciates his offer of further time; would pledge himself to complete the payment by January 1789.
    A. Mem., on fly leaf, by Dr. Franklin. "The opposition given more or less in every State to the propos'd Constitution, and from a Jealousy of Power, strengthens an Opinion of mine that America is too much enlightened to be enslaved; and thus the Happiness of its People is less in danger from an Excess of Power in the Governors, than from the Defect of due Obedience even to their own Laws, in the Governed."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Guillotin, Joseph Ignace
    Forwarding letters for Messrs. Saugrain [de Vigny] and Picque, for whom he begs a continuance of his kindness; their silence of fourteen months very alarming; begs for a line from Franklin. Desires information and advice concerning their choice of a place of their settlement; his desire to become an American citizen increased by the splendid work of the late [Constitutional] Convention; gives to Franklin the chief credit for the result; foretells a fairy future for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1788.] February 4 Monday; A.L.S. 3p.; Coxe, Tench
    Concerning the case of Miss Lydia Frazier, of Boston, who was placed as a day scholar in a convent at Auch in Gascony; induced by the nuns to commit herself to the religious life; as she is an American and under age, appeals to Franklin to help in the effort to return her to her relatives.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 6; A.L.S. 3p.; La Rouchefoucauld, Duc de
    His pleasure in knowing Mr. [Thomas] Paine; his bridge approved by the Academy [of Sciences]; is aiding M. Beaumarchais in the construction of a similar bridge at Paris. Affairs in France; much occupied with the meetings of Parliament; Edict in favor of non-Catholics a step towards tolerance; Assembly for the States-General announced for 1791. Desires the first volume of the [American] Philosophical [Society's] Transactions. Report of the ancient fortifications and other proofs of a previous civilization being found near Fort Harmar at the confluence of the Muskingum and Ohio rivers; desires to know if this is true. Messages from his host, the Abbé Rochon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Potts, Samuel
    Receipt for the balance of his account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Wethered, John. New Castle
    Asking for assistance to repair the Episcopal Church at New Castle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Picque, -----. Pittsburg
    Account of an attack of sciatica, which was much alleviated by the use of a root common to the country; offers to send a specimen to Franklin as a remedy for the stone; hears it has been extremely efficacious in such cases; not sure of the name; the savages call it "déje jon konā."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Irish politics; unbounded confidence placed by the whole nation in the Marquis of Buckingham; the last Viceroy one of the most abandoned, corrupt and profligate of men; no new pensions nor taxes; prevalence of gambling. Foreign politics; opposed to the Empress Catharine's ambitions; believes the Turks would suffer much before yielding the whole of the river Danube to the Sovereign of Hungary. Affairs in Holland. The English East India Co. afraid government will refuse a renewal of their charter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Moustier, comte de
    Received his appointment 1 on September 3d and left for Paris on the 10th of October; wished by this alacrity to prove his affection for the Americans and his eagerness to strengthen the bond between their two nations.
    1 Succeeded Comte de la Luzerne as Minister to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Ettwein, John. Bethlehem
    Presenting Franklin with a copy of the rules of their Society [for Propagating the Gospel]; their petition to the Pennsylvania Legislature for incorporation; recommends the Society and the Brethren's Church to Franklin's favor and protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Taillefert, ------. Nantes
    Account of a commercial transaction between himself and Pierre Charles Peyroux, and of the latter's failure to carry out his part; in 1785, M. Peyroux was at St. Louis, in the United States; desires that he may be made accountable for the debt he owes to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.